Guide to the Arena Stage records, 1949-2010
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
Arena Stage records
1949-2010
C0017
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
739 boxes
The Arena Stage records consist of material that spans the theater's history from its beginnings in 1950 to the present, including production notebooks, photographs, audiotapes, videotapes, playbills, scrapbooks, scripts, handwritten correspondence, and other production materials, as well as administrative records.
Arena Stage
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Some personnel records in Series 1 Subseries 3 Sub-subseries 2: Personnel, staff contain Social Security Numbers and must be screened by SCRC staff before researchers can view them.
Technical Requirements
The Special Collections Research Center does not have the equipment necessary to watch reel-to-reel film and audio, Betacam, or U-matic tapes contained in Series 5.2 and 5.3. Additional time and money may be required to digitize this material for access.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Arena Stage in 2000-2011.
Historical Information
From its opening on August 16, 1950, the Arena Stage has dedicated itself to being a space of imagination and innovation, a tool of "civilization," and Washington, DC's preeminent regional theater. Founded by Zelda Fichandler, with assistance from her husband Thomas C. Fichandler and partner Edward Mangum, the Arena Stage began as a for profit theater under Arena Enterprises, Inc. The original Hippodrome Theatre, located on Ninth and New York N.W. in DC, was revolutionary amongst regional theatres for its theatre-in-the-round construction and would provide the blueprint for all future Arena locations.
Arena began its long and successful life with Oliver Goldsmith's She Stoops to Conquer. Arena owed its early successes in the 1950s to its fluid play schedule organization and its willingness to put on works that were not commercial successes on Broadway. In November of 1956, after a year's hiatus, the company relocated to a temporary home at the Old Heurich Brewery, dubbed the Old Vat by company members. The move was facilitated in part by the commitment and drive of Board members J. Burke Knapp, Albert M. Berkowitz, Israel Convisser, Leslie Amouri, and Henry J. Danilowicz. However, financial issues would continue to trouble Arena Enterprises, Inc., eventually leading to its dissolution in 1959, and the creation of Arena's new, non-profit parent organization, the Washington Drama Society.
During the 1960s, Arena garnered international renown in its new space: the Arena Stage Theatre. The new building, located at Sixth Street and Maine Avenue SW, was the first playhouse built in Washington since 1895. Chicago architect Harry Weese designed the space to be as innovative as possible while still maintaining the theater-in-the-round layout. Now a non-profit theater, Arena drew much of its funding during this time from the National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) and generous donations from both the Ford Foundation and the Rockefeller Foundations.
The Arena Stage began some of its most ambitious work during the 1960s including forming the Living Stage Theater Company, further integrating its cast, and staging its most ambitious and acclaimed work to date: The Great White Hope. The Great White Hope included twenty five additional guest actors, including James Earl Jones, and was an enormous success, both critically and financially, for Arena. It was the first major resident theater production to be exported to Broadway. Fichandler also began to experiment with casting African-American actors in traditionally white roles during the 1968 season after she published the paper "Towards a Deepening Aesthetic". Fichandler experimented with non-traditional casting in plays like King Lear and The Threepenny Opera, but unfortunately these plays were met with critical confusion and disappointing ticket sales. Arena Stage was incredibly successful in the 1970s, garnering awards and critical approval, and international recognition. Not content with the current Arena Stage configuration, Fichandler and others worked diligently to acquire another stage facility that would collaborate, not compete, with the current Stage. Generosity on the part of David Lloyd Kreeger, and others, led to the construction of the new Kreeger Theater which opened on January 15, 1971.
In 1973 Arena would have the opportunity to take two of its plays, Our Town and Inherit the Wind to the USSR. This was the first ever trip to the Soviet Union undertaken by a resident theater group. The trip was a wild success with Russian audiences giving the cast a standing ovation following their performance of Inherit the Wind at the Moscow Art Theatre. In April 1976 the American Theatre Critics Association bestowed upon the Arena Stage a special Tony Award for resident theaters. The ATCA cited Arena's qualities as a "trailblazer" in theatrical arts and representative of other theaters that had followed its lead.
The early 1980s were a difficult time for theater, but, in spite of this, Arena continued to push the limits of conventional residential theater. The 1982 production of K2, for example, saw the construction of a sheer glacial face on the Kreeger stage according to the vision of set designer Ming Cho Lee. In 1986 twenty-three actors and a thirteen member production staff traveled to Jerusalem to perform Zelda's production of The Crucible at the Israel Festival.
1989 marked the end of an era as Zelda Fichandler announced that she would step down as Arena's producing director at the end of the 1990-1991 fortieth anniversary season. Douglas C. Wager would succeed her as artistic director. Amid financial difficulties and changing times for theaters everywhere, Arena's resident company of actors was disbanded by the late 1990s. Wager remained at the helm until 1998, when Molly Smith took over the position. Under Smith's leadership, Bing Thom architects completed another major renovation of Arena's existing buildings into the Mead Center for American Theater in 2010. Smith is still Arena's artistic director as of 2016.
Many now-famous actors took part in Arena Stage productions during the early part of their careers. Some of them include Robert Prosky, Morgan Freeman, Dianne Weist, James Earl Jones, Kevin Kline, Christopher Guest, Yeardley Smith, Samuel L. Jackson, Ned Beatty, Jane Alexander, and Ron Perlman. Many other set designers, artists, costume designers, and technical workers owe their early success and experience to the Arena Stage.
Scope and Content
The Arena Stage records consist of material that spans the theater's history from 1949 to 2010, including production notebooks, photographs, audiotapes, videotapes, playbills, scrapbooks, scripts, correspondence, and other production materials, as well as administrative records pertaining to the theater's finances, publicity, buildings, and programs.
Series 1: Administrative records (1949-2007) documents the creation, operation, and maintenance of Arena Stage and its various programs. It is further divided into 6 subseries. Subseries 1.1: Correspondence includes correspondence arranged alphabetically by the correspondent's last name or by organizational name. Some correspondence is further aggregated and then organized alphabetically, such as "Play Correspondence" or "Audience Response." Of particular note are letters from President Bill Clinton, Supreme Court Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg, and King Kong star Fay Wray. Subseries 1.2: Programs, policies, and procedures, includes records of Arena's programs, such as the "Arena Angels" volunteer program and fellowship programs, policies, such as bylaws, diversity policies, and handbooks, and planning, including season planning and long-range plans. This subseries is broken up into four sub-subseries. Sub-subseries 1.3.1: Financial papers documents Arena's finances and includes stockholder documents from its beginnings as a for-profit theater, grant-related documentation after the theater transitioned to a non-profit in the late 1950s, and records of the theater's development office, some of which were kept by department director Elspeth Udvarhelyi. Sub-subseries 1.3.2: Personnel records includes information on staff at Arena Stage arranged alphabetically. Of particular interest are headshots and/or resumes of a number of well-known actors, including James Earl Jones, Morgan Freeman, Henry Winkler, Edward Hermann, Yeardley Smith, Jane Alexander, Swoosie Kurtz, Victor Garber, Ron Perlman, Annette Benning, Olympia Dukakis, John Lithgow, John Voigt, Sigourney Weaver, and Rosemary Harris. Sub-subseries 1.3.3: Casting information contains notes on casting for productions arranged alphabetically by play. Sub-subseries 1.3.4: Production contracts includes official agreements between Arena and others arranged alphabetically by play. Subseries 1.4: Meeting minutes contains meeting minutes from Arena's Board of Trustees, staff, and other subgroups within the organization. Subseries 1.5: Communications and events, is also divided into four sub-subseries. Sub-subseries 1.5.1: Events documents special events held by Arena Stage, including anniversaries, galas, benefits, openings and press events. Sub-subseries 1.5.2: Communications and Marketing includes records produced by the Communications and Marketing departments, including meeting minutes, planning, research, and correspondence. Sub-subseries 1.5.3: Printed Material includes subscriber materials, mailings, brochures, reviews collected and arranged by play title, and programs organized chronologically. Sub-subseries 1.5.4: Theater Communications Group contains correspondence, reports, and other information generated from Arena's association with the Theater Communications Group, an organization of theaters around the United States. Subseries 1.6: Buildings and facilities includes information about and architectural plans for Arena's various buildings over the years, including the Hippodrome, the Old Vat, the 1960 permanent building, and the Kreeger Theater addition.
Series 2: Production Files (1950-2010) is comprised of records related to the artistic development and performance of Arena's plays. It is divided into 6 subseries. Subseries 2.1: Dramaturgical files documents literary, historical and background research done by Arena's literary department for various plays, including articles, research packets, actor's packets, and scripts. It is generally organized alphabetically by play. Subseries 2.2: Playwright subject files contains research on various playwrights, both living and dead, whose work has been performed at Arena. It is organized alphabetically by playwright's last name. Subseries 2.3: Production files includes scripts, blocking information, correspondence, and other material related to the production of Arena's plays. It is arranged alphabetically by play title. Subseries 2.4: Stage manager's reports includes daily reports by the stage manager of productions for the entire runs of many of Arena's plays from the late 1960s to the mid-1990s. The reports include running times, incident reports, and other commentary on the audience and the performance. Subseries 2.5: Wrap files contains documents collected from throughout the runs of various productions, including reviews that reflect the wider response to the play. Subseries 2.6: Producing director's files contains documents from Arena's second Producing director after Zelda Fichandler, Doug Wager, who served from 1991-1998. It includes pre-production speeches given by Wager, as well as planning files.
Series 3: Photographs (1950-1991)is divided into 3 subseries. Subseries 3.1: Production photographs includes photos of scenes from Arena's productions arranged alphabetically by play. Subseries 3.2: Production books includes production photos collected in books, many of which are by professional photographer George de Vincent. Subseries 3.3: Buildings, staff, and events includes photographs of Arena's buildings, staff and cast portraits, and event photographs, such as prints from Arena's 30th anniversary celebration and from Arena's Soviet Union and Israel tours. Subseries 3.4: Negatives and slides includes slides and negatives of Arena's staff and events, as well as some buildings, sets, and production-related images.
Series 4: Oversize (1949-late 2000s) is divided into 3 subseries and contains a variety of oversize material. Subseries 4.1: Braille programs contains programs in Braille for various Arena productions from the 1990s and early 2000s. Subseries 4.2: Miscellaneous artwork and programs includes posters from Arena productions and events, enlarged photos, costume sketches, and other oversized material, such as a large model of the Mead Center for American Theater. Subseries 4.3: Scrapbooks contains scrapbooks created for each of Arena's seasons up until 1988. It also includes scrapbooks for Arena's tour of the Soviet Union and of visitors to Arena.
Series 5: Audiovisual (1970-2007) contains several types of formats and is divided into 3 subseries. Series 5.1: Performances on VHS contains VHS tapes (a few of which have associated DVDs) of performances at Arena arranged alphabetically by play title. Series 5.2: Reel-to-reel contains production and event footage on reel-to-reel film. Series 5.3: Other audiovisual formats and VHS tapes contains footage of events and productions on audiocassette, Betacam, and U-matic tapes.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series, each of which is further divided into subseries:
Series 1: Administrative records, 1949-2007 (Boxes 1-196)
Series 2: Production files, 1950-2010 (Boxes 197-588, 654-663)
Series 3: Photographs, 1950-1991 (Boxes 589-639)
Series 4: Oversize materials, 1949-late 2000s (Boxes 640-720)
Series 5: Audiovisual materials, 1970-2007 (Boxes 721-739)
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives holds several collections of personal papers of individuals involved with Arena Stage, including the Zelda Fichandler papers, the Thomas Fichandler papers, and the Ken Kitch papers, as well as the Living Stage Theater Company collection and many other theater collections.
Bibliography
Maslon, Lawrence, editor. "The Arena Adventure: The First 40 Years." Washington, DC: Arena Stage, 1990.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Arena Stage (Organization: Washington, D.C.)
Subjects:
Theater--Washington (D.C.)
Document Types:
Photographic prints.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.
Contents List
- Series 1: Administrative records, 1949-2007 (Boxes 1-196)
  Scope and Content
  This series documents the creation, operation, and maintenance of Arena Stage and its various programs.
  - Subseries 1.1 Correspondence, 1950-2007
    This subseries includes correspondence, most of which is arranged alphabetically by the correspondent's last name or by organizational name.
    - 40th Anniversary - Chairman Letters, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 195-96 NEH Grant Correspondence, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Agency for the Performing Arts, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Alley Theatre, 1973-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - AM-RUS Literacy Agency, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Art, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Arts in Education, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Arts in Education, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - AT and T: On Stage, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Audience Response, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Audience Response, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Audience Response, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Audience Response, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Audience Response, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Audience Response (1 of 2), 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Audience Response (2 of 2), 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Audience Response (1 of 3), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Audience Response (2 of 3), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Audience Response (3 of 3), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Audience Response, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Auditions and Artist Management, London, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Emanuel Azenberg, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Lois Berman, 1979-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Bertha Case, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Bond Retirement Letter, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - George Borchandt, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Brandt #38 Brant Dramatic Dept. Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Bret Adams Ltd., 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Cafritz Foundation, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Canadian Embassy, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Chemical Bank, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Chronological Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Clinton/Gore, 1993-1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Rosica Colin Ltd., 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Comments/Criticism, 1968-1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Commissions, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Community Activities, 1970, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Complaints (1 of 3), 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Complaints (2 of 3), 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Complaints (3 of 3), 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Computers, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Consortium, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Consultation (1 of 2), 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Consultation (2 of 2), 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Curtis-Brown Agency, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Juby Daish Assoc., 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - DC Carol Correspondence (1 of 2), 2007 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - DC Carol Correspondence (2 of 2), 2007 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Directors at Arena A-D, 1988-1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Directors at Arena E-J, 1987-1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Directors at Arena K-L, 1992-1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Directors at Arena M-N, 1991-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Directors at Arena O-S, 1991-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Directors at Arena T-Z, 1977-1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Directors' Correspondence with Zelda Fichandler B-E, 1962-1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Directors' Correspondence with Zelda Fichandler K-S, 1958-1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Directors' Correspondence with Zelda Fichandler S-W, 1959-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Donor Correspondence and Fundraising (1 of 3), 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Donor Correspondence and Fundraising (2 of 3), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Donor Correspondence and Fundraising (3 of 3), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Donor Correspondence, Living Stage Arena, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Roger Downey, 1986-1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Ann Elmo Agency, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Faxes and Correspondence, 1990-1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - David Feiner, 1991-1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Fellows, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Fellows, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Fellows, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Fellows, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Fellows Project, Voices in the Threshold, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Fraser and Dunlop, 1982-1986 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Robert A. Freedman, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Samuel French Ltd., 1979-1985 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence (1 of 4), 1972-1979 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence (2 of 4), 1972-1984 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - General Correspondence (3 of 4), 1972-1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - General Correspondence (4 of 4), 1971-1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence - A, 1987-1993 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence - B, 1987-1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence - C, 1987-1994 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence - D, 1987-1994 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence - E, 1988-1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence - F, 1985-1993 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence - G, 1988-1994 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - General Correspondence - H, 1989-1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence - I, J, 1989-1995 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence - K, 1989-1993 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence - L, 1984-1994 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence - M, 1986-1995 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence - N, 1986-1994 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence - O, 1989-1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence - P-Q, 1987-1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - General Correspondence - R, 1989-1994 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - General Correspondence - S, 1986-1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - General Correspondence - T, 1989-1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - General Correspondence U-V, 1985-1993 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - General Correspondence - W, 1987-1994 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence - X-Y-Z, 1991-1994 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Ruth Bader Ginsburg, 1993-1995 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Eric Glass Ltd., 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Goodwin Associates, 1980-1985 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Graham Agency, 1979-1985 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Donald Graham, 1993-1996 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Great Northern Agency, 1979-1984 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Hesseltine/Baker, 1980-1985 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Tana Hicken, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Hal Holbrook, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Scott Hudson Inc., 1985 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - I.C.M., 1979-1985 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Michael Imison, 1979-1985 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - International Visitors (1 of 2), 1988-1995 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - International Visitors (2 of 2), 1994-1997 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Internships, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Lucy Kennedy, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Joyce P. Ketay, 1980-1985 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Dotty Kidder, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Bertha Klausner, 1979-1985 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Lucy Knoll, 1979-1985 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Yuko Kurahashi, 1996-1997 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - The Lantz Office, 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Floria Lasky, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Ming Cho Lee, 1993, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Sheila Lemon, 1979-1986 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - David Leong, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Tom Lynch, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Cormac MacCarthy, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Wendy MacLeod, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Cathy Madison, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Manhattan Theatre Club, 1979-1984 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Elisabeth Marton, 1980-1986 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Mary McAllister, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Heather McDonald, 1989-1994 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - MECCA by E. A. Whitehead, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Helen Merrill, 1979-1985 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - B, 1979-1985 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - C, 1979-1986 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - D, 1979-1985 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - E, 1979-1986 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - F, 1979-1986 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - G, 1979-1986 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - H, 1979-1985 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - I-J, 1979-1986 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - K, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - L, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - M, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - N, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - O, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - P and Q, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - R, 1979-1986 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - S, 1979-1986 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - T, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - U-V, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - W, 1979-1986 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence - X-Y-Z, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous/General, 1969-1981 (Box 9, Folder 13)